I knew this would happen, but after I became a second-year student, Mr. Hayashida was no longer my teacher.
I guess it's lunchtime now.
Hurry up! Before they sell out the double hamburgers and lunch sandwiches!
Well, I'm getting the fried chicken potato salad sandwich!
Ball is your friend!
I'm coming for you, world!
Hey, is it true he's a year older?
Then that means he's repeating the year, but I wonder why?
I heard that. He's really into shogi.
Is it shogi a game for old men?
A game played at home?
Is he an otaku?
Is he repeating because he ditched so much school?
Hmm, probably.
I... I gotta get out of here.
When the new school term started, everyone in my class immediately formed into groups.
They splintered off into little cliques and pretty much just kept to themselves.
So how is a loser like me with no courage or friends supposed to join any of them?
Hey, mind if I sit with you?
Was that weird?
Oh, no. More normal and less eager.
Hey, would it be okay if I ate with you?
Just like that. Nice and smooth.
As if I could do that, then I wouldn't be eating lunch by myself for 11 years!
Nope. It's impossible.
I'd definitely stumble like a dork.
Well, this is pretty much what I expected.
I'm just gonna have to bear it alone quietly.
Two more years.
Just two more years of being alone.
More importantly, the rank-deciding competition starts in June,
and I need to focus on my matches in the rookie tournament.
The rank-deciding competition.
There are 34 C1 players in my class.
Ten matches are arranged by lottery for those 34 players to participate in.
Only the top two players will be promoted to B2.
But Nikaida wasn't listed on the match schedule anywhere.
Kiriyama, what is this?
How should I know?
Are you at the Shogi Hall?
Wait for me, I'm on my way!
Now you and I are gonna have to go for it in the rookie tournament.
It's too bad that we're in completely separate blocks.
But, we'll just have to keep winning so we can meet in the finals!
Hey, wait!
What do you mean we'll meet in the finals?
Give me a break!
You can't make snap decisions like that!
Why not?
It's the truth, isn't it?
Now don't falter!
Hmm.
The legend between us...
has only just begun, trust me.
Legend?
And why is it ours?
Uh, yeah, sure.
Looking forward to it.
Yeah, I'll have to do my best.
Because that's all I can do.
For both the rookie tournament,
and the rank-deciding competition.
That's what I heard.
I think so.
Yeah.
I'll do my best.
One move at a time again.
Right from the start.
One move at a time.
Hey, Kiriyama!
Hold it right there!
Damn you, Kiriyama!
Mr. Hayashida?
What are you doing?
You shouldn't just abandon the students you were with.
I don't give a crap about that!
What am I supposed to do when I see a student look like that?
I have to run to his rescue!
You got it!
A student look like what?
I don't get it.
Come here!
It's written all over your face!
Are you kidding?!
So, um...
Yeah?
What?
So, is it...
all right for you to have lunch with me,
even though you're not my teacher this year?
Oh, yeah, sure.
I just saw my former introverted student
who barely passed the attendance requirement
due to certain circumstances
looking depressed.
When I told them,
the class said,
Mr. Hayashida,
you gotta help him!
Wait a minute, no fair.
Why are you making me sound like a big loser
while you get to be some kind of hero?
Because I want to be invited
to the students' Christmas party this year.
I've been feeling a little depressed, too.
But still,
why did you come back here,
Kiriyama?
It's a new year
and a new school term.
This is your last chance.
If you don't apply yourself now,
then when will you?
You are making an effort, right?
I sure hope so.
I can't encourage you to do your best
any more than that.
So,
I have a great idea.
Let's make our own Shogi Club.
Our own Shogi Club?
Huh?
But wait.
I'll be the faculty advisor.
If so,
then it wouldn't be strange
for me to look after you.
I'd be your advisor.
But that sounds easier said than done.
Just five members
and a faculty advisor makes a club.
Yeah, but still.
All we need are four more members.
But I don't know anyone
who would be interested.
Let's just look into it and see.
Okay.
But I doubt that'll be very easy to do.
You sound like a broken record.
Not at all.
It's nothing like that.
Ah, Kiriyama.
Why do you think you took another shot
at being a high school student this year?
Was it to
eat lunch all alone
sitting on the stairs like this?
Of course not.
Right?
Will this make it seem like
I'm not running away?
What if I'm only pretending
not to run away?
The truth is
it's always weighed heavily on me.
And I knew it too.
At this rate
things would only become
more painful for me.
I remember when it hit me.
I kept thinking
if only I could blend in better.
I wish.
Just imagine.
Imagine how happy I could be.
Mr. Hayashida.
Would you please be
the club's advisor?
Of course.
Oh, and Kiriyama.
I hope you know that
you'll be coaching me too.
Right?
Oh.
Okay.
All right.
There it is.
Free professional advice.
Great.
See?
I want to get beyond the wall
and I'm a fourth den.
There's this jerk
that I really want to beat on.
Net Shogi 24.
I'm confused.
Just a minute ago
I was moved by your kindness.
Nobody wants to join.
But why?
Is Shogi really that dull?
Everyone's like,
Shogi, sorry, I'm not interested.
What's up with that?
And I love it so much.
I'm sorry, sir.
There's no reason for you to apologize.
I kind of feel responsible.
That's it!
Noguchi!
Wow!
It stinks in here again!
Hello, Mr. Hayashida.
Long time no see.
What are you guys doing this time?
As you can see,
we're harvesting natto.
Okay, that's odd,
but why make natto here at school?
Well, you see,
we wrapped steamed soybeans
in rice straw
and keep them warm
at 100 degrees Fahrenheit overnight.
That allows the bacillus
to subtilize in the straw
and spread to the soybeans,
which proliferates fermentation.
Okay.
Well, I wasn't really asking you guys
about how you made it.
Wow!
Yup, this is the real deal.
You're eating that already?
Sometimes you can be surprisingly random.
Anyway,
how were you guys able
to find the rice straw?
I thought you'd never ask.
This is what I did for my thesis.
I grew a plot of rice
on the school roof last year
and then harvested the straw.
Wait a second.
What kind of thesis?
Who exactly are you presenting it to
and what is it even for?
And come on,
you know that's not allowed at school.
The entire concept is ridiculous.
Oh, wait!
I almost forgot why I'm here.
That's right!
Noguchi,
do you know how to play Shogi?
Shogi?
Well, my grandfather taught me
to play it when I was a kid.
And it's a rather intense game,
isn't it?
It is!
So here's the deal.
We're trying to put together
a Shogi club,
but we need four more members.
And now we finally got one!
Sounds like we're in the same boat.
The future of my
after-school burners club
is in peril.
The club could even be disbanded
at the next budget meeting
coming up in May.
What?
But I thought you had lots of members.
So what happened?
All of the upperclassmen
have graduated and moved on.
Wait a minute.
Those members were older than you?
Hello!
Is this the science club?
Teacher?
No, club president!
Yes, they were marvelous mentors.
From the day I joined the club,
even though I was
a first-year student,
they called me teacher.
I want to keep the club going
and have the opportunity
to pass the wonders of science
on to younger students.
But with only four members left,
it'll be the end of us.
No more.
If only I could complete my thesis.
Even if you did,
I highly doubt it'll pass on
the joys of science.
Hey, wait a minute!
I've got it!
We can join clubs!
Combine with us
and we'll create
a brand new club together!
Yes!
That makes sense!
All right!
And without further ado,
let's play a game!
I've been kind of holding back,
but now I can play
all the matches I want
with Kiriyama!
Since I'm the faculty advisor!
Ha!
Lucky me!
Noguchi,
I'm sorry.
Are you okay with this?
I feel like I'm imposing
on you again.
I'm actually kind of excited
about it.
After my grandfather
passed away,
I wasn't able to find
anyone to play with.
I'm still just a novice,
but I'd be honored
if you'd teach me too,
Kiriyama.
Yes, of course.
I'd be happy to.
And so,
the Afterschool Burners Club
became
the Afterschool Shogi Science Club.
This is how
my second year started.
A club.
A new club, huh?
And a shogi club at that.
Whoa.
See?
Just like I said.
After we left,
Mr. Hayashita said,
I find it easier
to do something
than just worry about it.
At least 80%
of the time it is.
His enthusiasm
gave me confidence.
The seat next to me
is always empty.
What?
I have to sit next to Kiriyama?
No way I'm doing that.
Teacher,
excuse me.
I have a question.
Can I change seats
and sit somewhere else?
Knock it off, Kaneda.
Just sit down.
Oh, come on,
teacher, please.
You heard what he said.
Hurry up and sit down.
There's lots of other seats.
You don't mind
if I move, right?
Fine, then please hurry up.
Yes!
Okay, everyone.
The class is leaving.
Hey, sit down right now.
At times like this,
I always feel like
if you don't want
to sit by me,
that's fine.
But you don't have to be so loud
and cause a scene
in front of everyone.
I know,
he's really loud.
But once the bus
started moving,
I began to feel
a little bit better.
After all,
it's much easier
to be left all alone
than it is to be forced
to sit next to someone
who hates you.
All right, everyone.
It's time for lunch now.
After lunch,
use the restroom
and be back at the bus
by 1.30.
Okay.
Good.
Be back in an hour and a half.
Dismissed.
Oh, no.
What am I supposed
to do here?
The field is huge.
There's no escape zone anywhere.
Eating my lunch all alone
in a wide open field like this,
there's nowhere for me to hide.
And if the teacher
finds me all alone...
Hey there, Kiriyama.
Why are you sitting there
all alone?
That's no good, right?
Please don't make me
the focus of next week's
homeroom assignment.
Everyone be nice
to Kiriyama.
What the heck?
That would be the worst.
It's tough enough
just having everyone hate me.
But to be put on display
on top of that
wouldn't solve anything.
It would only bring attention
to the fact
that everyone despises me.
No, I gotta avoid that
no matter what.
There.
It's kind of far,
but I'll go over there.
It'll be okay.
This'll work.
I'll just quietly walk
and not run.
If I just walk normally,
then I won't stand out.
Slowly,
normally...
I did it!
I made it!
It's cold
and damp.
I know.
I'll just use
one of my folders.
There are a bunch of ants.
Please,
don't crawl on my lunch.
I know.
There you go.
I wonder if ants
can even carry
a piece of candy that big.
I guess they have to
break it up
into tiny little pieces.
Sounds like a lot of work.
Huh?
I made a copy of this
from Father's book,
Checkmate in 117 Moves.
Oh, you solved it?
The one with 85 moves?
Incredible, Ray.
I couldn't figure out
how to solve that one
until I was in middle school.
My adopted father
is a professional shogi player.
He went pro
when he was 19.
I wonder if my father
will be happy with me
if I can solve
this problem, too.
All right, everyone.
Time to go.
Huh?
Um, is it 1.30?
I gotta clean everything up.
I hope I didn't leave
anything else
lying around here.
Oh, the ants.
They ate so much already.
Amazing!
I had no idea.
Even though the ants
are so tiny,
they melted away
the candy super fast.
Let's go, Kiriyama.
You're late.
Where were you, huh?
Sorry.
The bathroom was crowded,
so...
It's time for us to go.
Is everyone's seat neighbor
here now?
Yeah!
Wait, where's yours, Kiriyama?
Uh, no one was sitting here, sir,
so it's okay.
Oh, that's right.
Well, since everyone's here,
let's go!
Okay!
When I said no one
was sitting here,
I could feel a big lump
in the back of my throat.
I wonder
if the seat next to me
will always be empty
for the rest of my life.
All right.
Next seat five.
Have a good game.
For me,
that was it.
It was the magic ticket.
Good luck.
As long as I had that ticket,
somebody would always
automatically
sit right across from me.
I encountered
many different kinds of people.
Crap!
Who is this little brat?
You're too good.
Hmm.
Damn it.
I'll walk you to the station
since it's already dark.
Here, drink this.
Do you like cocoa?
Or what?
Uh, yes, sir.
Thank you.
Some acted like they were nice.
And of course...
Wow, you're pretty weak.
I wonder why Kota
would take you in
as his apprentice.
Some didn't like me at all.
But as long as I kept fighting,
someone would always
end up sitting in front of me.
This is the ticket.
As long as I have this,
I know I belong somewhere.
This ticket is my lifeline.
I don't have to go anywhere.
I can just keep on riding.
And that's fine with me.
If I get off this train,
I'll have nowhere to go.
This ticket alone
could take me all the way
to tomorrow.
So I have to hold on tight.
Like my life depends on it.
I have to protect it.
At all costs.
Hey, Kiriyama!
Kiriyama!
What are you spacing out about?
Come on, sit down.
He just made a move
and it was amazing.
Whoa.
Sacrificing the 5-3 pawn plus
was a great move.
With gold to same
and rook to 7-7,
what do you think
is next, Kiriyama?
How much time is left?
Mr. Fujimoto has 8 minutes
and Mr. Shimada
has less than 3.
First of all,
crush the rook at 7-7.
Then you take the initiative
by moving gold to 6-4.
Gold to 6-4?
Not the pawn at 7-3?
If you do that,
it'll be tough
against the bishop to 6-2.
It's not like I've changed, really.
And also...
the people around me
haven't changed, either.
It's just that,
while desperately playing
the game over and over.
Every single day,
it seemed like
my head would spin.
One day,
I realized
that other people
were traveling with me
on that train.
All moving toward
the shining light.